[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, again, the tradition, it's okay, but in the West, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just in regard to different things, maybe, maybe more specific views, as opposed to, like, genetic tradition, but it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: People get very upset, we point out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that you get upset on account of your dharma view, like, if you don't see that as a big problem, because there's nothing else you can, you can really discuss with that person, it's just
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I can get upset, you know, you offend me, you kick my doll, you do this, you do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you disagree with my dhamma views, if that bothers me, it means, well, those are not the views of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, it's remarkable the extent people... how far people would go, kind of knowing that, but ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, people hold their views so strong, and in the West, definitely, as much as any place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I mean, maybe it's a problem with the subjective perspective, attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe in America, especially, because things like existentialism and so on, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's wasting culture, generally, because... and in this universe, right, the education, mainly, you know, the way you grow up, the way you're taught in schools and stuff, you just end up being
[SPEAKER_00]: And no doubt, involuntarily, they're not aware of it themselves, but you end up being channeled in the direction of that kind of objective, sort of materialistic view, whereby, you know, if you really commit to it, you come to a point where you think your thoughts don't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The real thing is the only thing that is accessible through five senses, things that you can see.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to stop and think about what the senses are, you'll get very confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you wouldn't do it, you'll just keep going forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Into the things, into the science, into the everything, out there in the world, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is all based on the assumption that the world is there independent of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is a wrong assumption, because, you know, to have that assumption, you need to exist first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a contradicted assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was the main, like, line of existentialism.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sartre's saying, existence precedes the essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's just a big, like, no, whatever, whatever our thinking takes us,
[SPEAKER_00]: We need to come back to this first principle that existence precedes the essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't provide explanation, you can't develop an external view that will sort of, then in return, define your existence or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you need to exist first in order to do any of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means that's all secondary, which means you cannot stand for existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, they couldn't go further than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a huge change that happened to me with Yadavira.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just twisted everything around.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suddenly, these things make more sense to this world.
[SPEAKER_02]: I thought it was so real.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'm just, you know, a little thing in this world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Real is...
[SPEAKER_02]: I know the world through my own... through experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, experience is more fundamental than the objects that I'm...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm really just creating a model of a world from my experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: In as much as the objects of your senses define the domain of your sense, in that sense, they are also determined by those senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, if your eyes are not working or limited or whatever, they will limit the whole domain, the whole world of vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything you've ever seen, everything you will see, everything you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with any other sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is just that little material
[SPEAKER_00]: organ, sitting in a wall, same as that cup, same as that bin, same as the stone, eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as Aniruddha said, quoting that sutta, well, yeah, it's like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that they have this privileged position of it's an object in the world because of which there are objects in the world, because of which you see objects in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's an object in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice is really to remove that privilege from your senses, from your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: And which is why, whenever they're described, they're described in that kind of external terms, as a fleshy eye and organs and so on, because that's what they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't be more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the instrument in the world by which...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are the perceiver and the conceiver of the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have this weird thing happening in this minute.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not used to meditating so much, so I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: It probably doesn't mean anything, but... last couple of days, like, when my eyes are open and I'm seeing things, it's... sometimes it feels like I'm not looking...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not seeing objects, I'm seeing, like, images of objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that can be, I mean, true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a computer screen or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, for as long as
[SPEAKER_00]: When you say you're seeing images of objects, the objects that are now pushed in a background are not regarded as more real or more fundamental than the images of them that you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the problem, that the assumption can kind of take up anything in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, oh, these are just images.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if you say, well, your mind comes first, and people can get a hint of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the mind basically determines the experience as such, internal or external, or both.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, because just in that kind of little taste, little glimpse of that, that insight, so to speak, the assumption takes it out, and then you kind of overshoot the mark, and then you end up, everything is in my mind, like solipsism, no idea, the world is just in me, but you all exist just in my head, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that you can see that being remotely rooted in something that resembles the truth, but actually they overshot the mark and now it's just a just a view that misrepresents.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you see the images of objects, well, that's what's real for you at the time of seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the background of the objects just becomes another possibility of those objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words,
[SPEAKER_00]: The objects now, that are pushed to the side, because you've seen the image, become a possibility, a way that those objects can appear again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you see them as an image, then you see them as non-image, you see them as the real object, then they're just their modes of manifesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're all equally real as such in their own domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not that the real objects are more real than the images, because if you stop and think about it, even the real object is a metal image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not entirely.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is... it's founded upon the
[SPEAKER_00]: Four great elements, but if that image is not there, you wouldn't be able to even designate it as an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just couldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that is actually, again, that can be a very good practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the external things, the things that clearly define, the things that you access through your senses, to start recognizing the mental presence in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not just default to an assumption that there are solid objects out there, the way you see them and perceive them.
No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't mean that there is a hidden reality behind them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're real whichever way they appear, but you can't even conceive the idea of appearance if it's not mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it doesn't partake, at least to some extent, in a domain of mental and mentality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be the, I don't know, sañña and all that other stuff that comes in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today I had a strange thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Meditation has been very mild.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think because tired or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today my mind was wandering a bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I would have like an image just popped in my head.
[SPEAKER_02]: In this case, it was like a bowl of ice cream.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all at once, all together, the image, intense image, and then sort of the awareness that I was aware of it, and then this flame of desire, real craving, and then pleasure, strong pleasure, and it just sort of flush all at once, and three, four, five seconds later, it just disappeared, you know, and I went on to something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that was very interesting, and I started to play with that a little bit, because it was not an overwhelming kind of loss, but
[SPEAKER_02]: The one reason it was interesting is because I could really feel the feeling, the pleasurable feeling, and a lot of it... Well, that was the pure kind of example of delight, sensual delight, which is entirely mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your senses, they recognize agreeable and disagreeable, the five senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, they're like five animals, they have their domains, they want to... feeding grounds, how they call them, and they want to go after
[SPEAKER_00]: What they like to eat, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the eyes go out, the pleasant sights...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, that's only to a certain extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual notion of sensuality and the delight in sensual pleasures, that's what keeps you bound to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that the existence of the five senses is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's when you start to recognize, by seeing their delight, how actually it's the mental
[SPEAKER_00]: Take on pleasures associated with senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: That keeps you kind of enslaved to them, not the actual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, arahant could eat an ice cream, his favorite one, but he will not induce that mental delight anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean that he won't feel any pleasure of that pleasant, agreeable taste, but
[SPEAKER_00]: For the arising, for the ceasing, and for the persisting of that pleasure, at any time, he won't feel any delight associated with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another thing, comes down to what I said, when you have yet to start recognizing the mental image, the presentation, the dhamma, basically, in your thoughts and in things that you access through your senses, because they are determined as such, because of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you recognize the image of an ice cream and then the real ice cream, they have in common that they both appeared mentally, in a way, as a presentation of an ice cream, as an image of an ice cream, as a phenomenon of an ice cream.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the practice needs to pertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can't pertain just to you, generally, like dismissing your thoughts, or just thinking, or thinking this, you know, in response to that, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor can it pertain only to that which concerns the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, just say no to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just do not engage in any agreeable sensual
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sense experience, it's not necessarily sensual, because it will miss the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you free your mind on the level of that mental presentation, that dhamma, that phenomenon, that's in common to both, then you'll be free from both, whichever it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you think about ice cream, or you're actually eating the ice cream, it will not induce delight, which is that which keeps you bound, which is why its sensuality is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because usually people associate... ah, thinking is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when I think about it, I get all wound up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, yeah, you might do that once, but you won't be always able to stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you do come across ice cream, you just... well, there won't be much restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're restrained, even if you're just moderate and you just eat one spoon a day, still, you eat that one spoon a day with delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you eat no spoons at all, you will have delight in the earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why asceticism, per se, is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people just... the simile of the deer, the herd, in Majjhima Niṭṭhā, I think in the beginning, fourth, fifth sutta, when it says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The first group of deer eats the bait, the mara leaves, unwary.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just eat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't think, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that mother does with them what he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second group of deer, they see the first group and then they blame the bait, so then they completely shun the bait and they run into the mountains where there's no bait around to provoke them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But after a while, their energy, you know, goes down, not enough food, then they come back and they eat the bait unwarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the third group sees the first group, sees the second group, and says, well, what if we stay among the bait, but eat it carefully?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they do that, and then the mara, the hunter, comes, and he sees the bait eaten, but nothing is caught on the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he can't see those deer anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: They come and eat his bait, but he can't catch them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, then it says in the sutra, so then mara decides to leave them alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, try to harass him further, in case he harasses him further, they'll start telling everybody else how to avoid his bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a comparison to, kind of, obviously, sensual indulgence and then the form of asceticism, which is, kind of, a default mode for many monks, many people.
[SPEAKER_00]: All this bother me, you know, just, kind of, determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just say, you know, flirt with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can spend your whole life doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, you might not be, kind of,
[SPEAKER_00]: Going around naked, like those ascetics, or wearing a woodbag, or sleeping in thorns, and torturing yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that your mental attitude denies the bait, blames the bait, means you're not escaping it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're still hooked on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's impossible, really, for anyone in our hunt, as well, to... You can't not experience pain and pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wisdom of an Arahant is found in a completely different direction, or in the middle direction, which is basically saying yes to debate, saying no to debate.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it have in common, any of these reactions?
[SPEAKER_00]: It has in common the phenomenon of debate.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I free my mind in regard to the phenomenon of debate, if I see it as impermanent, as disagreeable, and as something that cannot be appropriated, and practice that long enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're among the bait or without the bait, you'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always say, that's what delight is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking that it's... Well, delight, you can... it's actually... it's delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delighting in the idea of engaging in something with your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's a pleasant taste, pleasant sight, pleasant
[SPEAKER_00]: Delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, allowing your mind to be overtaken by that, means you're delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're falling into it, which means... Well, it means you've been... you're hooked onto the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but if... if you remove the delight, the bait can stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be right in front of your face.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot pressure it into biting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you... you remove that by...
[SPEAKER_01]: By understanding objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding the phenomenon that's in common to the objects, whether externally, internally, or internally and external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding what appears?
[SPEAKER_00]: Phenomenologically, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not explaining it in terms of, oh, this is all impermanent, this ice cream, you know, it's gonna melt, it's gonna disappear in the sun, it was never real.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: An image of an ice cream, an image of a pleasant taste, an image of a pleasant sight, pleasant touch, that enchants, that has in common, in your mind, with the actual image, even if you're not actually looking at somebody or something, eating something, those things are...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't need exposure to sensuality in order to define sensuality, because it's defined by your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you actually need withdrawal from it in order to see that, like the main
[SPEAKER_00]: The main reason for being sensually bound is your mind, your mental assumption in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you approve that and then it's fine, even if you have things right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it comes down to being able to either think or directly experience through your senses a pleasant thing and not be taken by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being able to think or directly experience your senses unpleasant thing, and not feel aversion towards it, in terms of this kind of pressing need to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And extends down to what we spoke before about the neutral feeling, which is that where people... well, people don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, usually that's what's associated with boredom or with indolence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need excitement, or you need... well, you need anything, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you don't feel anything, you don't want to be resting on that feeling either.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's the important bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the subtle one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a form of delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I earned this rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: You did.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might have earned physical rest, but you've never earned, unless you're an arahant, a mental rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by mental rest, I mean giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when the Buddha gave that simile of a... of a cow with open wounds, that if it lays on the ground, it's eaten by the insects on the ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it lays... if it leans on the tree or a wall, it's eaten by the insects that live there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wherever... wherever he chooses to rest just for a second, it's being eaten by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the attitude you need to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, people, again, they overshoot the assumption, the mind, and you end up thinking it's just this constant tension that you have to live through.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can set your body to sleep, to feed it, take it for a walk, send it for a swing, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mentally, don't rest upon any of those actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And don't don't don't rest means don't lose mindfulness in regard to it, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't let your mind overtake it, and you forget about yourself, and then you really are taken by what you're doing, even if it's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unwholesome for that reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you are proved that you're like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you can notice, if your mind remains unwavered in regard to that subtle, neutral feeling, doesn't need anything, doesn't require anything, doesn't run away from anything, then when pressure arises, you'll be able to leave it alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the pleasure of the senses, the delight, is mental in regard to the sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one thing you can recognize is that no matter how great that sensual pleasure might be, it can never ever be anything more than what's defined by your sense organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be the greatest taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still a taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still dependent on the karmic.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it can never be more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be the most beautiful sight in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, when you forget that it's fully determined by the pair of fleshy eyes, you can have the whole image and the drama and the apprehension, the expectation and the realization of this great, you know, spectacle, because you lost sight of yourself and you're completely taken by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know that whatever you see, whatever you hear, whatever you taste, touch, smell, it can never be more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in seen, let there just be seen, in heard, let there just be heard, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Comes down when you recognize that, again, the entire spectrum of of sense objects, no matter how great it is, left, right, up, down, any direction, it's fully determined and cannot kind of step outside even a millimeter out of the sense organ domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is a six sense base, which some of the translations are like the fields.
[SPEAKER_00]: The senses are like the fields for these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be more than that, ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I mean, if I...
[SPEAKER_00]: But not knowing there cannot be more than that, you delight at the prospect of being more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that delight can pull you, push you, make you pursue the senses,
[SPEAKER_00]: But in the end, all you're going to get is sense and its object.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I agree with... which is why usually people out there giving in to desire is like, oh, was that all?
[SPEAKER_00]: The expectations are always higher because that's... that's how the mind... that's how the life works.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's nothing unusual about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually quite normal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, not knowing that, you associate that delight, that expectation, with this prospect of that sensual desire, a fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that that delight takes you in the domain of that sense that has its own scope.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eyes cannot experience anything more than sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ears cannot get you anything more than pleasure of a sound.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the greatest, the most refined?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still a sound.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing of pleasure, the feeling perception, by... if you think ice cream, there's a pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, every time you think ice cream, there's a feeling, every single time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That seems to suggest, in my mind, that there is, you know, there is something there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the pleasure is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why does it... why is it always connected with any particular perception or image?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it can be random, it can be circumstantial, because you try and ask you and you really like it, because there is such a thing as a pleasant taste by default.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is, your question, why is this connected, assumes that the connection between the two is somewhere... somewhere inside of the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you, kind of, unravel it all, then you will be able to, kind of, cut those wires and it will not be... that's not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem... the problem... well, the question you ask is... is a symptom that you are already affected by those... by... by... by the perception of ice cream.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your response to the fact that you don't know the escape from the ice cream.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know gratification in that regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't recognize the danger and you don't see the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, yes and no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of those acts are just response... your ways of responding to the fact that you're already touched by that... by that phenomenon you're taking back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever... whatever is perceived, there is a feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always a feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling and perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're trying to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're trying to separate them, so you're not affected by it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing is, you have to go the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by the other way, I mean, by seeing, perception and feeling are inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they arise on their own, means, well, you can wonder for the rest of your life, why is the thought of ice cream always pleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you can just accept that,
[SPEAKER_00]: And instead of questioning that, try to find a place whereby you don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by that, I mean, you don't care, not in a sense you ignore it, but in a sense, perception of pleasant ice cream doesn't bother me anymore, doesn't touch me anymore, doesn't command me anymore, doesn't make me do things anymore, doesn't make me think things anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot overtake me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then,
[SPEAKER_00]: You might wonder why is it pleasant, or you might not wonder that, but that would be irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only reason you're wondering that now, is because you do realize, you do recognize the problem of being pulled by your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So your question is kind of trying to solve it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you actually solve it the proper way, questions become redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not why is it always pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should really ask yourself, why, why am I being touched by that, by that image?
[SPEAKER_00]: By that pleasure, why am I being... why is it controlling me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it better if I'm... well, if I get over it, so to speak, why is it better if... if I find a way where that pleasure cannot access me?
[SPEAKER_00]: You think about that, and you will start to recognize the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will start to recognize the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: And gratification is what I was speaking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not loving gratification means confusing your delight with the actual, like, sensual consumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize that no matter how great the delight is, gratification remains confined to the domain of a particular sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot... it's inconceivable for it to be anything more, despite what, you know, your delight makes you expect.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure of a sight cannot be experienced by anything other than your eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize, ah, that's the extent of gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you recognize the danger as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Expecting more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, through that expectation of more, you blindly jump back into those domains that are not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going between the eye and sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going between the nose and smells, ears and sounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, basically, it's just like running in the middle of a motorway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is not yours, but you don't know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just run right in the middle, and then something will hit you sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what the Buddha compared killing into sensuality like putting your head on a chopping block, where the axe falls, and it will fall.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither that perception, nor that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're wondering, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: How did that come about?
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you already took it as mine, which that's where the mistake is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not finding out the answer to those particular questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't help, you can't just stop and will the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not engage in sensuality anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I guess you could do that if you develop jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, through them, you could think that, and then you could stand for that determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: But otherwise, you have to recognize gratification, the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it dangerous if I give in?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will offer the the site of escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, if I remove the delight in this... not in regard to the whole world, just in this particular sense, in these five senses, you're not chasing after every object.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the delight in the eye, because of which you delight in the sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you recognize it's fully confined to your eyes, fully confined to your ears, you remove delight in regard to that, and you go, okay, I am free from this, because no matter how much it arises,
[SPEAKER_00]: It can never, sort of, well, go behind me and, kind of, scoop me out again, as it used to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why there's a simile in the suttas, when the Buddha compares a... well, somebody who's free from sensuality, lives like a... like a drop of water on a plate, on a sharp plate, but it's not cut by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the five senses, basically, entirely, which means your whole world, really,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not actually yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: It belongs to the mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: The eyes in your head, ears, nose, tongue, body, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what it sees, hears, touches, smells, tastes, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mara is the determinant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, those things are, in and around, undetermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the determinations have ceased.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't become the undetermined.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just cease to act as determinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Determinations of his self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is just another way of saying, he stops taking it as his.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they have ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: He left... he leaves them be.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ceased to exist as me and mine, and determining me and mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what the undetermined is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if there wouldn't be undetermined, freedom from determined would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because there is the undetermined, freedom from determined is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the ādhāna doesn't create nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just kind of finds a way to step into it, because it's already there, the undetermined.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you step to it, through developing full knowledge of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another question that was sort of related to this, was probably the wrong question, but... that everything seems to...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it corresponds.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can feed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I can touch it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can experience it through different senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they correspond.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's very easy to assume that it's one thing out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Indriya said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either things usually appear as a self, when it's seen twice, either in reflection or experienced simultaneously through two different senses or more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, then they're confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why ignorance means going with the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the direction of the stream.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you go against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to practice correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go against by holding it, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you go against it by full understanding, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no method or something, but full understanding that each domain, each sense, if that's what your approach is, means, yeah, it would be... well, it wouldn't be inducing the sense of self anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, actually, the self that appears when a thing is seen twice in deflection,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the self of that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The self-identity of the same thing that you hear and that you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sameness
[SPEAKER_00]: You assume to be neither in what you see, nor in what you hear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's the same self-think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Myself is experiencing the sameness of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Myself is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Myself is independent of any other thing that I experience through my sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it kind of goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm using senses to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will have to be able... which is what I mean when I talk about the principle of simultaneity in the notes of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you simultaneously, here, see something, if your mindfulness is established properly, you'll be aware of it as two independent but simultaneous domains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they don't actually meet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of your senses, ever, on their own, they all kind of come together in your mind, but in their own domains, they're just like... Well, as I said in another essay, in regard to fire, indifferent to each other, it's just not even a... like, there is not even awareness in your hearing, in your hearing of your sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because having awareness of your sight in your hearing would be
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, your sight appears in your hearing, even as a possibility, even as a different domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why you have five consciousnesses in regard to five senses and then six ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have six types of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, when I...
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: When, if I see something, hear something, and then, and also touch and experience...
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine six layers of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I...
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still seems like there is a paying different attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, from this center here.
[SPEAKER_00]: From one... Yeah, because you give... you still have the assumption of me and myself as the core of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to keep developing mindfulness as long as it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, well, as I said before, when you feel that core, you can't start straight onto the senses now, the contemplation I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can come later.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just too subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you would have to take up the experience as a whole and then include in that, that sense of core, that sense of center, which is sense of me and I am, as a phenomenon, as a peripheral phenomenon, without making it actual, all that we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by including it, bit by bit, you become aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the time will come when you recognize, well, if I'm aware of it, means it appears as a phenomenon, which means it will cease as a phenomenon, which means it can't possibly be me or anything related to me in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just everything is just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a sight, it's an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's independent of the senses, which is how it has that assumed privileged position over that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you stop and think, as we spoke before, this body, this physical body right here, which basically covers up the basis of the senses, the five senses, and then the experience, the general experience as a whole, in my sense of self or whatever else,
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that be conceivable in any shape or form if this physical body is to be destroyed next instance?
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the privileged position and attitude is slowly being undermined.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can... you're not even denying the sense of privilege of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You include it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you make sure it gets undermined with the right... with the right...
[SPEAKER_00]: Settle with the right insight, with the right reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, in the ānāpānasati, I will breathe in like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe so you keep including yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep including yourself in the next breath, in this breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, do it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're including your very volition and intention, while you're seeing clearly that even the most
[SPEAKER_00]: The strongest willed thing, the most determined thing, well, could have never been yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's simply no room for the for self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not just there's no room, it's not necessary at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why there is no room for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's a... you said that birth is intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you pay attention to the birth, you find that it's really intending.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can find that, but as long as you include your sense of self in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens is, people would kind of forget about itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it would be, oh, breathing just happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's this thing breathing me, or it's this body breathing... All that is... you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not inaccurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you left the sense of self out of it, means you're not really addressing the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like getting the decent medicine,
[SPEAKER_00]: But applying it over a covered-up wall, so it doesn't actually reach the point where it's supposed to be active.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you keep including your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep bringing it forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not letting it kind of wiggle out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the same as the contemplation I described to you, when you recognize, okay, this body is right here, right now, in this situation, in this position, in this shape or form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully, fully material.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, entirely composed of elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely nothing in this body that doesn't pertain to one of the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a hundred percent object, because of which you're thinking of what objects are, and that right reflection, while you're thinking, stands there, because of that random object, like that kettle, like that bottle, like that cup.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something happens to it on that material level,
[SPEAKER_00]: In which you have no access at all, you realize nothing can remain standing, even the greatest sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, establish your mind upon that, and by establishing your mind upon that, I mean, in the beginning, you have to keep bringing it up, then you fall from it, you bring it up, but then you bring it up, and that thought, that perception of that relationship stays.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, ah, the mind is established to a degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you lose it, bring it back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Could one say that in recognizing that the sense of self is sort of derivative of like the different senses, sort of different senses pointing to that one focal point, and then recognizing that this impermanence of the sense is a way to get to realize that that sense of self, which is derived from it, is
[SPEAKER_00]: That's solid.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can be, for as long as you first acknowledge that focal point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's real, as such, and it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because usually people would resort to contemplation of impermanence of a kind, to obscure, or to deny, or to cover up, or to remove that focal point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's there, it means it has a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever has a reason means it wants to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no interference with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were to contemplate impermanence like that, yeah, it will point out that this focal point is not... well, it cannot be taken as me and mine, because it's fully dependent upon these external organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have no control over.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that can become valid only after that focal point has been acknowledged and recognized as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people often get too quick to say, there's no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no self, no self, no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is self.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is focal point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what no self is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like throwing out the self.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're throwing out the whole problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like a scientist, just pure objectivity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're ignoring the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I meant before when you asked about meditation the other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever arises, you include that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever arises, well, it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, trying to exclude it is a mistake, just for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have no say over things arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you would, well, there would be a sense of self then.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they manifest when they manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you stop trying to interfere with that, if you recognize that whatever has a reason, you will see that for those very reasons of simple arising, that's why it will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So impermanence actually is in arising of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, not like looking and waiting for their destruction to prove that they're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they're impermanent because you're experiencing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And to recognize that whatever is arising, it's... it's complex.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like an integrated system.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything integrated has to disintegrate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not even that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's... that's another designation that you will put on top.
[SPEAKER_00]: System integrated or simple or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: The most accurate you can get is saying, it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the most accurate phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't have to go further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't actually go further than that, because any other more elaborate explanation would be sort of going back down and then providing an explanation for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: An explanation, even if it's a very pleasing one, is still an explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it has to... it has to be recognized on that general level where it just arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for that very reason, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no say in its manifestation, which is why it will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that's recognized, then everything, whether it's particular or general, is seen through that principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the sense... and that... the very sense of self arises depending on... on these things that arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you recognize... because you recognize principles in regard to anything that manifests.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that reason, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... well, yourself manifests.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ambiguous, general, not specific, yet, it's manifested as such, thus, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can... with me, it doesn't even occur anymore, oh, this is my... it cannot even be assumed, even be thought of or fantasized anymore as myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inconceivable, becomes, when that principle is understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what Sister Vajira meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, she lost the dimension of her soul.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's just... Well, actually, she didn't quite lose it fully, back then, but she's clearly recognizing it, because if she lost it, she couldn't have even remembered it, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't even bring it back as a memory, because even the preview, the memory and the past is seen as impermanent, which means your self ceases to reside even there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the dimension is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Sotāpanna cannot even remember what... well, he can recognize what Atavāda is, assuming self out of the five aggregates, but he cannot even conceive that, even as a memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows, oh, I used to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I used to, like, I used to think that I existed, independent of my senses, independent of my aggregates, but actually, how that
[SPEAKER_00]: What's experienced actually, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot arise anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why past and the future and the present get affected with the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: The real key is seeing, seeing how
[SPEAKER_02]: This sense of self is depending upon these rising and falling phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the standard view for Kutujan, I think, is that I'm here, solid, and I'm experiencing all these things, and whether they come and go, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... and that would be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what the Buddha meant by impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the point is, no, the impermanence has to be personal, which means the impermanence has to pertain to that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're contemplating something that's coming and going, and you don't feel anything, that's... that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to find the impermanence that will concern you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, the thought of this thing disappearing will concern you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what I mean, impermanence, like if you... like seeing a thing manifest, and then seeing the destruction of the thing, it's actually another... another arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a manifestation, appearance, of a thing being... of a particular thing being disintegrated.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it's actually more arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a worldly type of impermanence, in terms of things have changed their shape, or whatever else, but, terminologically speaking, it's just another arising experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't actually experience impermanence through your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any, in any way, you can't even conceive it, the true impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you would, you would need the Buddha to tell you how to find the way out of the self-view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to
[SPEAKER_00]: As most of the mystics believe, and hopeful, that's a sin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, through a vision, through mental or whatever, and it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of trying to see disappearing, you recognize that the appearance is the disease, because of which it's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be gone, even if it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it is, that's another experience that has arisen, because it has arisen, the impermanence is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: That which you regarded as permanent is also impermanent, and even the impermanent things that you regarded before are even more impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just impermanence and more impermanence, as opposed to impermanence and then too much of permanence.